Guide to the Lynne Sagalyn Research Files for "Power at Ground Zero" 19xx-2xxxx MS 3128
New-York Historical Society
Lynne Sagalyn research files for "Power at Ground Zero"
19xx-2xxx
New-York Historical Society
Sagalyn, Lynne B.
MS 3128
.01 Linear feet in ...
TBD
Arrangement
TBD
Biographical / Historical
TBD
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lynne Sagalyn, February 2019.
Scope and Contents
TBD
- Series I. Episodes (E) Files, 19xx-2xxx; 2 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  "Episode," or E series files include newspaper articles (clippings, tear sheets, print-outs from newspaper websites or other on-line sources), miscellaneous primary and secondary materials (press releases, magazine articles), and some notes by Sagalyn related to various aspects of Ground Zero redevelopment. These include the design considerations and debates,
  - EO. July leasehold sale to investor group, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - E1. 9/11 Collapse, 2001-2002, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - E2. 9/11 Recovery Effort, 2001-2002, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - E3. 9/11 Corporate Reaction, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - E4. 9/11 Real Estate; E5. 9/11 Rebound (over time), 2001-2004, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - E6. Designs I; E7. Designs RFP II, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - E8. Land Swap, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - E9. New York Times Design Initiative, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - E10. Years Later (anniversaries, nostalgia). (3 folders), 2002-2014 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - E10-10. Tenth Anniversary (2 folders), 2005-2013 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - E11. Designs II, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    See also WTC Commercial Design Guidelines document in Box X.
  - E11b. Semi-final Round, 2001-2003, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - E12. Libeskind Master Plan, including Implementation Struggles (slurry wall) (2 folders), 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - E13. Environmental Impact Study (EIS), 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - E15. Transit Building – Temporary PATH Station Rebuilding (Church Street), 2001-2003, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - E17. Cultural Program ICI, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - E19. Permanent Calatrava and PATH Station Design (2 folders), 2003-2015 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - E16. Expanding the Site (Deutsche Bank Building); E16b. 130 Liberty Deconstruction / Fire (2 folders), 2002-2008 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - E20. Freedom Tower Design (> Dec 16, 2003) / E24 Freedom Tower Redesign, Architects Battle (2003), 2003-2015 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - E21. Stalled/Delays, 2004-2013 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - E25. Cultural Buildings and Dissembling Events, 2004-2015 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - E25. Cultural Buildings and Dissembling Events / RB6. Rebuilding: Cultural, 2004-2015 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - E26. Construction Starts / Progress Steps, 2005-2013 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - E27. Goldman Sachs Deal and Building; E28. Cortland & Dey Streets Debate, 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    See also Series V. Rebuilding Files for the related 2005 Goldman Sachs lease document.
  - E30. Power struggle: Bloomberg's calls and criticism of Silverstein, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - E31. Pataki Deadline / Lease Renegotiations / Conflict leading to Episode E34, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - E32. PA takeover of project's construction management / PA problems with delivery of sites; E35. Paterson Timetable / News of Ward Reports, 2005-2009 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - E37. St. Nicholas Greek Orthodox Church resolution / deal collapse, 2001-2015 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - E40. Port Authority / Silverstein Financing Conflict, 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - E41. The "stumps" – podium; E 44. Third Amended to the Port Authority-Silverstein deal, 2010-2012 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - E45. Park51 Mosque Conflict, 2010-2011, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - E46. 10th Anniversary / Memorial Plaza opening, 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    See also E10-10.
  - E47. Port Authority audit 2010, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - E50. Merrill Lynch/JP Morgan potential tenancy, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - E51. Superstorm Sandy, 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - E53. Achievements / Openings, 2007-2016 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - E55. Openings of Rebuilt Facilities, 2011-2015 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Includes Greenwich Street/Courtlandt Way, PATH Terminal, Tower 4, Memorial Museum, Liberty Park, and Miscellany.
  - E56. 3WTC Proposed Recast Deal, 2014-2016 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Transit Hall articles and critique materials used for epilogue, 2003, 2014-2016 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series II. Port Authority of New York and New Jersey (PANYNJ), 19xx-2xxx; 1.5 Linear feet
  The series includes primary documents related to the Port Authority, including Board resolutions, committee minutes, legal opinions, memorandums, reports created by the Port Authority and others, arbitration decisions, press releases, etc. While some material relates to the Port Authority generally, much if not most of this relates specifically to the rebuilding of the World Trade Center transportation hub and to chapter 15 (Transportation Phoenix) in Lynne Sagalyn's book. Primary documents also include summaries of interviews conducted by Sagalyn. The series also includes Sagalyn's chronologies, notes, article logs, and other work product based on these documents.
  Arrangement
  tbd
  - Two States in the Board Room, 1979-2000, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Documents underlying part of Chapter 4. Includes articles, etc. dated 1979-2000, with Sagalyn's 2013 chronology and log of WTC sale/privatization articles.
  - Privatization reports (2 folders), 1984-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    Includes repors from Bear Stearns, Chemical Securities, legal analyses, and others.
  - Port Authority document binder (3 folders), 1993-2015. (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    Includes Board resolutions, agreements, memorandums of understanding (MOU), and other materials from 1993-2015. Also, includes Sagalyn's summary of actions at PANYNJ board meetings of October 2006-April 2009.
  - Commissioner Anthony Sartor voting record & related documents (2 folders), 2001-2015 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    Includes Sagalyn's 2015 log of Sartor's voting record, 2001-13, with underlying documents: Board material for Downtown Restoration Program, 2001-13, and Committee of Operations, 2009-14.
  - Transportation Phoenix (3 folders), 2002-2014 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
    Sagalyn's notes, chronologies, news and articles log and analysis, with underlying source documents, related to Chapter 15.
  - WTC Transportation Hub documents (2 folders), 2003-2014 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Reports: "World Trade Center Assessment" and "World Trade Center Report: A Roadmap Forward", 2008 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Delivery problems (3 folders), 2008-2013 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
    Includes Sagalyn's chronologies, notes, article log, analyses, and interview notes, with underlying source documents, including among many others the Hub Working Group Steering Committee Final Report of September 25, 2008 and arbitration-related material.
  - WTC Tower 3, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes Sagalyn's notes and transcripts from Board meetings in 2014.
  - Net leases and financing, 2001-2010 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Credit rating, 2006-2012 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Financial documents (2 folders), 1980-2003 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    Includes an audit of PANYNJ employee compensation plans (1980), audit report regarding toll increases (1981), PA Bus Terminal investment analysis (1999), financial statement for 2001, and official statement for Series UU notes (2003).
  - P8. Politics: PANYNJ, 1976-2015 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
  - Press releases, 2003-2011 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series III. Lower Manhattan Development Corporation (LMDC), 19xx-2xxx; 1 Linear feet
  The series includes materials that center on the development of downtown, most especially as it related to the role of the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation (LMDC). Documents include press releases and other documents produced by or about the LMDC; planning and redevelopment-related documents, such as the World Trade Center General Project Plan (GPP)and Environmental Impact Statement (EIS); and Sagalyn's notes, chronlogies, and other work product related to the source material.
  - New York City Department of City Planning (DCP) / Deputy Mayor Daniel Doctoroff, 2002-2004 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - City Council Committee on Lower Manhattan Redevelopment, 2006-2013 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes Committee meeting briefing papers and summaries prepared by Sagalyn and research assistants.
  - Transcript of minutes of the City Council's Committee on Lower Manhattan Redevelopment, 2006 March 9 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - LMDC Background, 2002-2011 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Includes by-laws, webpage and other print-outs of LMDC Board member biographies and other organizational information, and speeches by its executive officers. Also includes a list of LMDC Board minutes available online through 2011 and a CD labeled "LMDC minutes."
  - P13. Players: LMDC (3 folders), 2001-2016 (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
  - 130 Liberty Street Deconstruction, 2003-2008 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Includes overview, chronology and other material prepared by Sagalyn's research assistant. Includes a CD of documents downloaded by the RA, with a summary list in the file and some print-outs, including speeches and Committee briefing papers. See also Episode E16b in Series I.
  - P13b. Players: Lower Manhattan Construction Command Center (LMCCC), 2004-2013 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Includes notes from one interview, with other documents, mostly news articles.
  - LMDC press releases, 2002-2005 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Includes a few releases for 2002-05, but a log of releases for 2001-11 prepared by Sagalyn.
  - PP2. Plans & Planners: Process - General (2 folders), 2001-2015 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - LMDC various documents (2 folders), 2002-2013 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    Documents related to the performing arts/cultural center; a summary of community development block grants; LMDC/PANYNJ brochure re: design studies (2002); an agreement between the city and PANYNJ re: World Trade Center PILOT (payments in lieu of taxes) and re: design guidelines (both 2006); and various correspondence re: Sagalyn's requests.
  - LMDC Chronology: WTC Rebuilding Effort, 2001-2013 (2 folders), 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    Includes Sagalyn's chronology, cross-referenced to source documents found in various files. This file holds certain documents from 2002-05.
  - World Trade Center General Project Plan (GPP). including amendments, and Environmental Impact Statement (EIS) materials (3 folders), 2033-2007 (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - World Trade Center Generic Environmental Impact Statement (EIS) (2 folders), 2004 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
- Series IV. Commercial Real Estate and Silverstein Properties, 19xx-2xxx; 1 Linear feet
  The series includes documents centered on the rebuilding of the World Trade Center towers, especially as it related to the involvement of developer Larry Silverstein and Silverstein Properties. Documents include agreements with Silverstein-related entities; media clips about Silverstein; and news articles, other published material, and presentations about commercial real estate and its economic prospects in lower Manhattan post-9/11.
  - 1 World Trade Center Lease, 2001 July 16 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - P14. Players: Silverstein Properties. Various documents, 2002-2014 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Includes the interim access agreement between the Port Authority and various World Trade Center limited liability companies (LLCs), 2002; legal and other documents regarding leases and easements, 2003-07; news articles, 1987-13; public statements by Larry Silverstein; and Sagalyn work product, including notes, interview questions, and media log, 2001-14
  - Silverstein Properties. Media clippings and presentations (2 folders), 2005-2010 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
    Includes two packets of media clips from Silverstein Properties; slides of a presentation "Building for the Future" by John N. (Janno) Lieber of Silverstein; and a press packet, with CD, of materials titled "Completing the Vision" in connection with the unveiling of WTC designs by architects Norman Foster, Fumihiko Maki, and Richard Rodgers (2006).
  - World Trade Center deal realignment materials (2 folders), 2006 (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
    Includes NYC Economic Development Corporation's WTC Summary of Financial Analysis presentation to the City Council, with Sagalyn notes; letters from Silverstein properties to the Port Authority; the NYC Independent Budget Office's analysis of anticipated demand for space in a rebuilt WTC site; Port Authority board documents; master development agreement; and articles and Sagalyn media log.
  - RB5. Rebuilding: Commercial real estate (5 folders), 2001-2015 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
    Includes McKinsey's 2002 PowerPoint report "Revitalizing Lower Manhattan" to the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation; a report by Hugh F. Kelly for the Civic Alliance on downtown office prospects after 9/11; published reports by Cushman & Wakefield and others; and news articles/clippings.
  - RB5-1. Rebuilding: Commercial real estate: Freedom Tower / 1 World Trade Center (4 folders), 2004-2015 (Box 6, Folder 6-9)
    Includes a set of documents concerning the development and management of the 1 WTC observation deck, including the Request for Proposal (RFP) and lease with Legends Owo, LLC; Port Authority Board authorization of a joint venture with the Durst Organization; articles and clippings; and some Sagalyn and research assistant notes.
  - RB5-2 through RB5-5. Rebuilding: Commercial real estate: Sites 2, 3, 4, 5, 2006-2015 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series V. Rebuilding (RB) Files, 19xx-2xxx; 1.5 Linear feet
  Includes
  - RB3. Tourism, 1995-2012 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - RB4. Transportation (Mass transit, Hard rail). Reports, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - RB4. Transportation. Infrastructure, 2001-2002, 2010-2011 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Includes news clippings and work product of Sagalyn and a research assistant.
  - RB4. Transportation (2 folders), 1993-2015 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    Includes Sagalyn and research assistant article abstracts and chronology, as well as many clippngs and articles.
  - RB4-1. Transportation: Fulton Street Station, 2003-2007 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - RB6. Cultural (Freedom Center, Drawing Center), 2002-2012 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - RB7. Economics, including Lower Manhattan, 2002-2015 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Includes, among clippings and other print matter, a CD of Sagalyn's 2005 paper/talk at the Wharton (UPenn) Real Estate Department on "The Politics of Planning the World's Most Visible Urban Redevelopment Project" and a CD of the 2002 Urban Land Institute fall meeting on "New York One Year Later."
  - RB8. Insurance; RB8-2. Litigation, 2002-2014 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - RB9. Incentives; RB19. Cost/Economics, 2001-2010 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - RB10. 7 World Trade Center, 1984-2012 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - RB11. Skyscrapers, 1983, 2001-2004 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Includes, among clippings and other documents, transcripts of panel discussions on "Building in the Aftermath of 9/11" held in 2002 at the National Buiding Museum.
  - RB14. Polls / C15. Commentary: Ballots, 2001-2014 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - RB15. Financing / Liberty Bonds (3 folders), 2002-2012 (Box 7, Folder 6-8)
    Includes, with print matter, Sagalyn and research assistant work product including chronology and accounting of the $8 billion bond authorization.
  - RB16. Housing, 2002-2013 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - RB17. West Street, 2002-2009 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - RB18. Retail, 2001-2015 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Includes Port Authority Board documents related to joint venture agreements with Westfield America Limited Partnership and Westfield Ameruca Inc., with Sagalyn research assistant notes and other print matter.
  - RB22. Context: History, 2001-2012 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - RB25. Legal issues (other than insurance; includes allegations of fraud), 2004-2012 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Includes Sagalyn and research assistant work product summarizing WTC disputes/litigation. Includes some print-outs of articles and CD of Summer 2010 WTC articles.
  - RB26. Security, 2001-2013 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - RB27. Environmental; RB29. WTC Utility Restoration & Infrastructure Rebuilding Program (as amended August 2004), 2001-2005 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - RB30. Construction Technical Achievements and Mishaps, including underground; RB39. Fiterman Hall, 2004-2015 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Battery Park City Authority lease to Goldman Sachs Headquarters LLC, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Includes lease for development of trading and office space, as submitted with Goldman Sachs Form 8-K of August 23, 2005, with related documents.